Preliminary Guide to the James Applewhite Papers, 1963-2010 RL.10163
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
James Applewhite papers
1963-2010
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Applewhite, James
RL.10163
13 Linear Feet
James Applewhite is a poet and professor emeritus of English at Duke University. The collection is comprised of manuscripts, drafts, and proofs of poems, as well as notes, correspondence, clippings, and printed materials (including serials and anthologies). The collection documents Applewhite's work as a poet and professor of English at Duke University, including his research about Wordsworth. Manuscripts in the collection include Lessons in Soaring: Poems, A History of the River: Poems, and River Writing: An Eno Journal.
9825 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted. Written permission is required to view correspondence and business records. Contact Research Services with questions.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The James Applewhite Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 1993 and 2010.
Biographical Note
James W. Applewhite is a poet and professor emeritus of English at Duke University. He has published several books, including Statues of the Grass (1975), Following Gravity (1980), Foreseeing the Journey (1983), Seas and Inland Journeys: Landscape and Consciousness from Wordsworth to Roethke (1985), River Writing: An Eno Journal (1988), Lessons in Soaring (1989), Daytime and Starlight (1997), Selected Poems (2005), and A Diary of Altered Light (2006).
Chronology List
1958 B.A., Duke University
1960 M.A., Duke University
1960-1963 Instructor, University of North Carolina at Greensboro
1967-1971 Assistant Professor, University of North Carolina at Greensboro
1969 Ph.D., Duke University
1970 National Endowment for the Arts Award
1972 Assistant Professor, Duke University
1974-1975 National Endowment for the Arts Fellowship
1975 Associate Professor, Duke University
1976-1977 Guggenheim Fellowship
1979 Associated Writing Programs Contemporary Poetry Prize
1982-1985 Director of the Institute of the Arts, Duke University
1986 North Carolina Arts Council Fellowship
1988 Professor, Duke University
1992 American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters' Jean Stein Award in Poetry
1995 North Carolina Award in Literature
1995 Election to the Fellowship of Southern Writers
2008 Induction into the North Carolina Literary Hall of Fame
2009 Emeritus Professor, Duke University
Poets, American -- Correspondence; Poetry -- Publishing -- United States; American poetry -- 20th century; Poets, American; American poetry -- North Carolina; Duke University. Department of English; Chappell, Fred, 1936-; Duke University -- Faculty; Dickey, James; Applewhite, James; Applewhite, James; Applewhite, James -- Statues of the Grass; Applewhite, James -- River Writing; Applewhite, James -- Lessons in Soaring; Stuart, Dabney, 1937-; Ruark, Gibbons; McFee, Michael; Hall, Donald, 1928-
- Accession (1993-0285), 1964-1992, 5 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  The collection is comprised of manuscripts, drafts, and proofs of poems, as well as notes, correspondence, clippings, and printed materials (including serials and anthologies). The collection documents Applewhite's work as a poet and professor of English at Duke University, including his research about Wordsworth. Manuscripts in the collection include Lessons in Soaring: Poems, A History of the River: Poems, and River Writing: An Eno Journal.
  There is no boxlist for this accession. Access is RESTRICTED: Written permission is required to view correspondence and business records.
  - Accession (1993-0285) (Box 1-5)
- Accession (2010-0155), 1963-2010, 10 boxes
  Includes correspondence files, writings (both published materials and drafts), photographs, biographical/bibliographical lists and files, and other miscellaneous materials.
  - Correspondence, 1960s-2005
    Contains correspondence with literary figures and publishers. Frequent correspondents include Dave Smith, Donald Hall, Dabney Stuart, Fred Chappell, Robert Bly, James Dickey, Michael McFee, Gibbons Ruark, and others. Also includes 1 folder of Pulitzer Prize jury correspondence. This material has been loosely arranged into folders by year, but has not been sorted by date within each folder.
    Conditions Governing Access note
    This material may be RESTRICTED. Contact Research Services with questions.
    - Correspondence, dates unknown (Box 6)
    - Loose poetry sent and received, dates unknown (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, 1960s (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, 1970-1976 (7 folders) (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, 1977-1984 (10 folders) (Box 7)
    - Correspondence, 1985-2005 (9 folders) (Box 8)
    - Pulitzer Prize jury correspondence, 1977-1979 (Box 8)
  - Published Materials, 1968-2010
    Applewhite's publications in poetry journals and other anthologies.
    - "The Door, The Wind," and "Station and Flame," The Above Ground Review, Vol. 1, No. 1, November 1968 (Box 9)
    - "An Episode of War" and "Versions of Sunlight," Granite, No. 1, Spring 1971 (Box 9)
    - "A Long Poem" and "Selections from Notebooks," Crazy Horse 12, 1972 (Box 9)
    - "At Raleigh Memorial Gardens (Post Christian Era)," The Back Door, No. 7/8, 1975 (Box 9)
    - "Visit with Artina," Michigan Quarterly Review, Spring 1975 (Box 9)
    - "Desire," The Agni Review 4, 1975 (Box 9)
    - "The Rescue," Sandlapper, Vol. 9, No. 2, February 1976 (Box 9)
    - "Elegy for a General Store" and "Woman in the Wind Knows," Vanderbilt Poetry Review, No. 3/4, 1977 (Box 9)
    - "Following Gravity," The Cold Mountain Review, Vol. 5, Fall 1977 (Box 9)
    - "Seven Poems," The South Carolina Review, Vol. 10, April 1978 (Box 9)
    - "A Broken Lake" broadside, 1983 (Box 9)
    - "The Body Garden," Mudfish, 1984 (Box 9)
    - "Accident of Inheritance," The Ohio Review, No. 45, 1990 (Box 9)
    - "Botanical Garden: The Coastal Plains" and "The Mortal Father," The Southern Review, Vol. 33, No. 1, Winter 1997 (Box 9)
    - "On Winslow Homer's 'Weaning the Calf,'" Southern Cultures, Vol. 3, No. 2, Summer 1997 (Box 9)
    - "Poet to Poet: The Perspective of Poetic Voice," The Writer, December 1997 (Box 9)
    - "Hank Williams Dream," "Birdfoot," and "Rain from a Hurricane," The Southern Review, Vol. 38, No. 2, Spring 2002 (Box 9)
    - "River-Ruin," "The Vanished Farmhouse," "Christmas by the River," "Fall Will," "Looking Up from the Woodland Clearing," and "Ceremony at Heroes' Square," North Carolina Literary Review, No. 13, 2003 (Box 9)
    - "Blossoming Poplars," North Carolina Literary Review, No. 19, 2010 (Box 9)
    - "My Grandfather's Funeral," in Leland H. Roloff's The Perception and Evolution of Literature, 1973 (Box 10)
    - "Poems," North Carolina Literary Review, No. 6, 1997 (Box 10)
    - "Birthday Poem," Cold Mountain Review, Vol. 36, No. 1, Fall 2007 (Box 10)
  - Writings
    Mostly consists of loose poetry and other manuscripts. Includes manuscript drafts for "Following Gravity," "Iron Age Flying," "A Journal of Sunlight," "Steps to the Stream," "Driving through the Country America that is Vanishing," "Landmind," "Gift of Inheritance and Other Poems," as well as some drafts of essays and articles. Other materials include Applewhite's notebooks and notepads, many with poetry or drafts, as well as some with notes, schedules, to-do lists, and other miscellaneous writings.
    - Reviews (photocopied compilations) of Applewhite's works, 1975-1987 (Box 10)
    - Articles and essays, 1985-1986 and undated (Box 10)
    - Poetry and other manuscripts
      - Photocopies, undated (Box 10)
      - Loose poems, undated (3 folders) (Box 10)
      - Statues of the Grass manuscript (Box 10)
    - Poetry and other manuscripts (Box 11)
      - Following Gravity, undated (3 folders) (Box 11)
      - Iron Age Flying, undated (5 folders) (Box 11)
      - Untitled book draft, undated (Box 11)
      - A Journal of Sunlight, undated (Box 11)
      - Steps to the Stream, undated (Box 11)
    - Poetry and other manuscripts (Box 12)
      - Steps to the Stream (2 folders) (Box 12)
      - Driving through the Country America that is Vanishing, 1973 and undated (3 folders) (Box 12)
      - Landmind, undated (2 folders) (Box 12)
      - Gift of Inheritance and Other Poems, undated (Box 12)
      - The Magic Life essay (Box 12)
      - Loose poems, undated (6 folders) (Box 12)
    - Unpublished novel: Alive in Time, undated (3 folders) (Box 13)
    - Poetry and other manuscripts
      - Driving through the Country America that is Vanishing, undated (2 folders) (Box 13)
      - Legal notepads with drafts and ideas (10 folders) (Box 13)
    - Poetry and other manuscripts (Box 14)
      - A History of the River, 1988 (Box 14)
      - Notepads with drafts and ideas, 1988-1991 and undated (3 folders) (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous Files, 1960s-1980s
    Includes Applewhite's research files and some research papers, his applications for various fellowships, and recommendations he wrote for his students. Also includes biographical and bibliographical details, photographs, newspaper clippings, and magazine addresses.
    - Research papers, 1963-1964 (Box 14)
    - Notes for thesis/dissertation (15 folders) (Box 14)
    - Applications for fellowships (Box 15)
    - Recommendations by Applewhite (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - Bibliographical/biographical materials, 1970s-1980s (3 folders) (Box 15)
    - Magazine addresses, 1960s-1970s (Box 15)
    - Photographs, 1960s-1970s (Box 15)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1969-1971 (Box 15)
- Accession (2013-0039), 1980-2008, 5 boxes
  Includes writings (both published materials and drafts), professional materials (including photographs, information about events, & awards and honors), correspondence -primarily with publishers and journal editors, extensive notes, and other miscellaneous materials.
  - Writings
    This series contains drafts and notes related to Applewhite's writings. There are a number of legal and notepads containing drafts of both poems and prose works, as well as letters. The materials include voluminous notes and drafts for Applewhite's Cosmos and Creation. The series has been organized into two subseries: one for prose and one for poetry.
    - Writings: Poetry Drafts (Box 16)
      - Loose Poems, undated (12 folders) (Box 16)
      - Creation: The Inhabited Cosmos (5 folders) (Box 16)
      - Cosmos, or States of transition (2 folders) (Box 16)
      - Cosmos, or States of transition (2 folders) (Box 17)
      - The War with My Father (Box 17)
      - A Diary of Time (Box 17)
      - Quartet for Three Voices (Box 17)
      - Session in the Sand Hills (Box 17)
      - Poems on England (Box 17)
      - Compass for the Flood (Box 17)
      - The Life of Mary (Box 17)
      - The Earth Outside My Office Window (Box 17)
      - A Diary of Slanted Light (Box 17)
      - A Diary of Altered Light (Box 17)
      - A Shadowed Coutenance (Box 17)
      - Garden Poems, The Country Song, & The Space of Earth (Box 17)
      - New Poems, Fall 2004 & 2005 (Box 17)
      - Legalpads with Drafts, Notes, & Ideas (7 folders) (Box 17)
      - Recent Miscellaneous Manuscripts, 1955 (Box 17)
      - Earliest Complete Version of "Gift of Inheritance" (Box 17)
      - Older Manuscripts in Progress (Box 17)
    - Writings: Prose Drafts (Box 17)
      - On Southern Writing and the Problem of the Father (Box 17)
      - Recalling a Trip with V.S. Naipoul, The Places and Words of a Poem & Poetry and Memory (Box 17)
      - A Consciousness of Time (Box 17)
      - Lifew of Emily Dickinson, The Last Modernist Poet, & On Books and Houses (Box 17)
      - Loose Notes & Drafts (Box 17)
      - Music of the Falling, a Novel (3 folders) (Box 17)
      - "American-Type" Painting and Poetry in the 1950's (Box 18)
      - The Style of Art (Box 18)
      - Legalpads with Notes, Ideas, and Drafts (10 folders) (Box 18, Box 3)
      - Emotion and the Language of Poetry (Box 18)
      - Echo, Memory, and Poetic Authority (Box 18)
      - Consruction a Surface: Stylistic Authority in Eliot (Box 18)
      - Wallace Stevens and His Recent Critics & Editors (Box 18)
      - Art's Way of Beholding (Box 18)
      - Signifier/Signified & the Writer's Relation to Place (Box 18)
      - The Poet at Home in the South (Box 18)
      - Postmodernist Allegory & the Denial of Nature (Box 18)
      - Epilogue: What is the Good of Writers? (Box 18)
      - A Southern Modernism & Its Underground Vision (Box 18)
      - A Problem of Consciousness (Box 18)
      - The Gothic Horror/Apocalypse (Box 18)
      - The Phases of Composition (Box 18)
      - The Near Landscape & the Far: Nature and Human Signification (Box 18)
      - Poetry, Values, & Value (Box 18)
      - Duke and the Idea of Greatness (Box 18)
      - Reviews of Others by Applewhite (Box 18)
      - Criticism, Poetry, & Biology/Seeing Like a Poet (Box 18)
      - Poetry & Physicality (Box 18)
      - A Boundary-Crossing Lyric, Cultural Identity/Spiritual Identity, and The Rope-Like Stream of Time (Box 18)
      - Poems in Place and Time (Box 18)
      - The Southern Sense of Time (Box 18)
  - Notes
    This series includes various handwritten and typed notes by Applewhite. The notes pertain to Applewhite's academic career, teaching, writing and planning, and drafts of correspondence. There are also several lists of addresses and contacts. Many of the notes are in legalpads, spiral notebooks, and small bound notebooks.
    - Loose Notes (2 folders) (Box 19)
    - Legalpads (9 folders) (Box 19)
    - Small Notepads(2 folders) (Box 19)
  - Publications
    This series contains Applewhite's own published works, including manuscripts, reviews, and advice from other authors.
    - Reviews of Applewhite's Work (Box 19)
    - Draft & Response for "American-Type" Painting & Poetry in the 1950's (Box 19)
    - Steps from the Stream (Box 19)
    - A Long Poem: Published in Crazy Horse (1992), Three Poems: Published in Carolina Quarterly (1966) (Box 19)
    - A Consciousness of Time: Preface (Box 19)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 19)
    - Notes (Box 19)
  - Correspondence
    The correspondence series includes Applewhite's letters to publishers, acceptance and rejection letters, submission lists, and miscellaneous correspondence with colleagues and friends from approximately 1980-2008. Publication related to specific works is labeled as such, with the rest of the series organized by year.
    Correspondence and business records are restricted for the life of the donor. Contact Research Services for details.
    - Publication Correspondence Re: The Human Style (Box 19)
    - Publication Correspondence Re: River Writing (Box 19)
    - Publication Correspondence Re: Coordinate/Cosmologies & Poetry (Box 19)
    - Publication Correspondence Re: A History of the River (Box 19)
    - Publicaiton Correspondence Re: Daytime & Starlight (Box 19)
    - Publication Correspondence Re: Lessons in Soaring (Box 19)
    - Publication Correspondence Re: Quartet for Three Voices (Box 19)
    - Komunyakaa Visit, March 2001 (Box 19)
    - Rejection Letters (Box 19)
    - Acceptance Letters & Submission Lists (Box 19)
    - Royalty Statements (Box 20)
    - Publicity Statements (Box 20)
    - Undated (Box 20)
    - 1970s (Box 20)
    - 1980s (Box 20)
    - 1990s (Box 20)
    - 2006 (Box 20)
    - 2007 (Box 20)
    - 2008 (Box 20)
    - 2009 (Box 20)
    - 2010 (Box 20)
    - 2011 (Box 20)
  - Professional
    The professional series contains materials related to Applewhite's academic and literary career. These materials include interviews, photos, biographies of Applewhite (by himself and by others), grant applications and notes, information on events attended, and awards and honors.
    - Interview with Betty Adcock (Box 20)
    - Duke Blackburn Literary Festival (Box 20)
    - NEH Application, 1974 (Box 20)
    - Courses (Box 20)
    - Essays and Biographies on Applewhite (Box 20)
    - Awards and Honors (Box 20)
    - Events (Box 20)
    - Photos (Box 20)